<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on My New Hugo Site</title>
    <link>http://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on My New Hugo Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 19:35:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution of critical care physician workforce in North Carolina</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/critical_care_medicine_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 19:35:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/critical_care_medicine_covid/</guid>
      <description>As North Carolina prepares for possible future waves of COVID-19 cases requiring hospitalization, @WorkforceNC is committed to providing data on the availability of critically needed health professionals, such as critical care nurses, respiratory therapists,infectious disease specialists and primary care access. Health systems in North Carolina are acting quickly to boost the numbers of health care professionals, ICU beds, and equipment. This blog post represents the best available data as of May 21st, 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>North Carolina’s Supply of Critical Care Nurses are Crucial to the State’s COVID-19 Response</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/icu_nursing_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 13:12:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/icu_nursing_covid/</guid>
      <description>As North Carolina (NC) prepares for a rising number of COVID-19 cases, @WorkforceNC is committed to providing data on the availability of needed health professionals. Check out our blogs oninfectious disease physicians and primary care access.
High numbers of COVID-19 patients will strain the health care system’s critical care and emergency medicine capacity, sharply increasing demand for hospital Intensive Care Units (ICU) beds and staff. Along with ICU beds, ventilators and personal protective equipment (PPE), NC needs the nursing workforce to care for the high influx of critically ill patients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>North Carolina’s Respiratory Therapist Workforce: Availability to treat COVID-19</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/respiratory_therapist_nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 18:05:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/respiratory_therapist_nc/</guid>
      <description>As North Carolina prepares for a rising number of COVID-19 cases requiring hospitalization, @WorkforceNC is committed to providing data on the availability of critically needed health professionals, such as critical care nurses and infectious disease specialists. Health systems in North Carolina are acting quickly to boost the numbers of health care professionals, ICU beds, and equipment. This blog post represents the best available data as of April 3rd, 2020.
NPR recently reported that 2% of those who contract the coronavirus develop respiratory issues that require a ventilator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primary Care Access in North Carolina is Not Equally Distributed </title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/primary_care_nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 19:24:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/primary_care_nc/</guid>
      <description>Primary care practitioners per capita is one of the NC Institute of Medicine’s (NCIOM) 21 health indicators for the Healthy NC 2030 project. Access to primary care is necessary to improving the health outcomes of communities. With the recent spread of the novel coronavirus in North Carolina, primary care is critical as an entry-point to further care. Many rural areas of North Carolina lack adequate access to primary care providers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19, Primary Care, and Infectious Disease Physicians in NC</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/infectious_disease_md/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/infectious_disease_md/</guid>
      <description>The first cases of coronavirus (COVID-19) have been documented in NC. The spread has sparked concerns about public health infrastructure. Adults aged 65 and older are especially vulnerable to coronaviruses and the subsequent respiratory infections they can cause. During an epidemic like this one, primary care is the entry point to testing and to referral if more intensive and specialized care is necessary. In North Carolina, primary care clinicians are unevenly distributed, with access worsening in rural areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How diverse is NC&#39;s obstetric delivery workforce?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/obstetric_provider_race/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 20:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/obstetric_provider_race/</guid>
      <description>In 2018, 21% of NC&amp;rsquo;s population identified as black or African American, compared to 13% of the state&amp;rsquo;s obstetric delivery providers. Similarly, 10% of NC&amp;rsquo;s population identified as Hispanic or Latino in 2018, compared to 3% of NC&amp;rsquo;s obstetric delivery providers. Additionally, only five black family medicine physicians reported providing routine obstetric delivery services in 2018. In North Carolina, infant mortality rates are higher for non-Hispanic black babies than for non-Hispanic white babies, and this gap has persisted for nearly 20 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do we know about graduate medical education (GME) outcomes in NC?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/nc_gme_outcomes_summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 17:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/nc_gme_outcomes_summary/</guid>
      <description>North Carolina’s population is growing fast, with 10% percent growth since 2008. The number of physician residency slots is growing even faster. Over the past decade, the number of residency positions in NC has grown by 14%.   NC does not have a physician shortage, but physicians are maldistributed in the state (see previous blog post). NC’s physician-to-population ratio is increasing but most of the growth is in urban areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC&#39;s physician-to-population ratio is increasing, but most of the growth is in urban areas.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/physician_growth_metro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/physician_growth_metro/</guid>
      <description> The number of physicians in NC has grown over time, outpacing population growth. The main concern is not the overall number of physicians in North Carolina, but the distribution of physicians in the state. Most of the growth in physicians per capita has occurred in urban counties. In rural (non-metropolitan) counties, growth in physicians per capita has been slow. Access-to-care issues remain concerning in many rural and underserved places.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do NC’s international medical graduates come from?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/growth_of_imgs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/growth_of_imgs/</guid>
      <description>International Medical Graduates (IMGs) are physicians who received their medical education outside of the United States, Puerto Rico, or Canada. As of 2018, 15.5% of North Carolina physicians are IMGs. This is below the national median of 19.1%. The number of IMGs in North Carolina has more than doubled since 2000. IMGs from Pakistan have tripled, and IMGs from Nigeria have more than tripled. In 2018, North Carolina had six times the number of IMGs educated in the Caribbean as it did in 2000, but a majority of these physicians are United States citizens who sought medical education outside the US.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where were North Carolina&#39;s Occupational Therapists Trained?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/ot_training/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/ot_training/</guid>
      <description>Occupational therapists (OTs) treat patients with physical, developmental, or cognitive disabilities, focusing on the patient&amp;rsquo;s ability to perform activities for daily life. OTs work with patients in homes, schools, workplaces, and healthcare facilities. A master&amp;rsquo;s degree is required for an OT to become licensed. National OT organizations recently considered requiring a doctoral degree but determined that both a master&amp;rsquo;s or doctorate can be accepted as the entry-level OT degree. North Carolina does not have a doctoral OT program and fewer than 100 of the OTs in NC are doctorally trained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dentist workforce in urban counties is younger than the workforce in rural counties.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/age_dentists_metro_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 14:47:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/age_dentists_metro_2018/</guid>
      <description>In 2018, 87% of NC dentists practiced primarily or exclusively in metropolitan counties. There are more younger dentists than older dentists in metropolitan NC counties. This finding implies that new dentists have consistently gravitated toward practice in urban rather than rural areas. See our prior blog post for more on this trend. The age distribution of rural dentists is relatively even, with a slight uptick for dentists in their mid-60’s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maternal &amp; Fetal Medicine FTEs per 10,000 Population By County</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/mfm_fte_map_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/mfm_fte_map_2017/</guid>
      <description>Maternal and fetal medicine is a subspecialty of Obstetrics and Gynecology (Ob-Gyn) focused on high-risk or complicated pregnancies. &amp;ldquo;High-risk&amp;rdquo; means the mother or fetus is at risk of problems during pregnancy or delivery due to a chronic disease, an infection, problems with previous pregnancies, a pregnancy-related health condition like preeclampsia, or another reason. As with many subspecialties, maternal and fetal medicine physicians tend to concentrate in urban areas, near hospitals and academic health centers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nurse Practitioner (NP) and Physician Assistant (PA) Schools in North Carolina</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/npandpaschools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 18:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/npandpaschools/</guid>
      <description>North Carolina has nine NP schools and eleven PA schools, with a twelfth PA program at Pfieffer University scheduled to open in January 2020.
 Including Pfieffer University, seven of the PA programs opened in 2011 or later.  As part of their education, NP and PA students complete rotations at clinical sites with preceptors: experienced NPs, PAs, and physicians who supervise and mentor learners.
 The number of qualified preceptors has not kept pace with the rapid enrollment increases at NP and PA schools, creating a difficult situation for NP and PA programs across NC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Since 2000, Growth of North Carolina&#39;s Nurse Practitioners (NPs) and Physician Assistants (PA) Has Outpaced That of Physicians.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/growth-of-nps-pas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/growth-of-nps-pas/</guid>
      <description>The total number of NPs and PAs in North Carolina is less than the number of physicians, but new NPs and PAs are entering NC&amp;rsquo;s workforce faster than physicians are. Between 2000 and 2017, the NP workforce grew most rapidly, increasing by 216% in non-rural counties and by 187% in rural counties. After 2014, the gap in workforce growth between non-rural and rural counties widened for both physicians and PAs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compared to Non-AHEC Residents, a Higher Percentage of NC AHEC Residents are Practicing in NC</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/ahec_resident_outcomes_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 16:58:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/ahec_resident_outcomes_2017/</guid>
      <description>53% (n=1,135&amp;frasl;2,157) of physicians who completed an AHEC residency between 1997-2017 were practicing in NC in 2017 41% (n=4,561&amp;frasl;11,233) of physicians who completed a non-AHEC residency between 1997-2017 were practicing in NC in 2017 Compared to non-AHEC residency graduates, a larger percentage of family medicine physicians, general internists, and pediatricians* who graduated from an AHEC residency were in NC in 2017  Notes: Data include active physicians in the 2017 AMA Physician Masterfile who reported completing residency training in North Carolina between 1997 and 2017.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution of Psychiatrists Across North Carolina</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/psychiatry_fte_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 19:41:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/psychiatry_fte_2017/</guid>
      <description>North Carolina has 1.2 psychiatrist FTEs (full-time equivalents) per 10,000 population. Orange County has 9.8% of the psychiatrist FTEs in North Carolina, but only 1.4% of the population. Granville County, home to one of the three state psychiatric hospitals, is also an outlier. Unlike our health professional supply map, which assigns heath professionals to counties based on primary practice location, this map accounts for psychiatrists who practice in multiple counties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>North Carolina Psychologists by Age and Sex</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/psychologists_by_age_sex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/psychologists_by_age_sex/</guid>
      <description>Nearly a quarter of psychologists are 65 or older (compare this to physicians where only ~12% are 65 or older).
60% of the psychologists who are 65 or older are male, but 70% of those younger than 65 are female.
New entrants to the profession are predominantly women. Four out of five psychologists who are 45 or younger are female.
  
import {Runtime, Inspector} from &#34;https://unpkg.com/@observablehq/runtime@3/dist/runtime.js&#34;; import define from &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which North Carolina counties have older populations?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/percent_65_and_older_map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/percent_65_and_older_map/</guid>
      <description>Use the slider bar below the map to scroll through years 2000 to 2037 and see the changes by county.
In rural counties, the proportion of the population older than 65 has grown faster than it has in urban counties, particularly in the Western and Northeastern regions of the state.
Counties with larger metropolitan areas tend to have a greater proportion of younger residents.
Hoke and Onslow counties are projected to have the lowest proportions of adults 65 and older in the state by 2037.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aging of the Physician Workforce</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/md_avg_age/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 15:25:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/md_avg_age/</guid>
      <description> The average age of a physicians in North Carolina has steadily increased since the year 2000. The rural physician workforce is aging at a faster pace than the metro workforce. In 2000, only 1.5 years separated the average age of metro and rural physicians. By 2016, rural physicians were, on average, 4.2 years older.    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking the Workforce Outcomes of NC Medical Schools Five Years After Graduation: Class of 2012</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/nc_mst_classof2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 18:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/nc_mst_classof2012/</guid>
      <description>Of the 436 NC medical school graduates from the class of 2012, 1% (n=4) were in practice in primary care in rural NC five years after graduation. This finding is similar to prior years. All four physicians in primary care practice in a rural county were family medicine physicians who graduated from a public medical school: two each from East Carolina University and the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill. Primary care includes family medicine, general internal medicine, general pediatrics, internal medicine-pediatrics, and obstetrics &amp;amp; gynecology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mission Matters: In-State Retention of NC Medical School Graduates</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/ncmedschoolretention2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 16:05:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/ncmedschoolretention2016/</guid>
      <description>The Brody School of Medicine at East Carolina University has a legislatively mandated mission: to increase the supply of primary care physicians to serve North Carolina. Only North Carolina applicants are considered for admission to ECU. Consistent with this mission, a higher proportion of ECU’s graduates practice in-state compared to other NC medical schools. The language in the mission of each medical school is aligned with the relative proportion of graduates who practice in NC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC&#39;s Public Medical Schools Retain More Graduates In-State Than Private Medical Schools Do.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/med_student_cohorts_retain_nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 18:30:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/med_student_cohorts_retain_nc/</guid>
      <description> Compared to other medical schools, a higher percentage of each graduating class from East Carolina University practices in NC. ECU&amp;rsquo;s legislatively mandated mission is to increase the supply of physicians for the state and only NC residents are considered for admission.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC&#39;s Dentist Workforce Has Grown, But Only in Well-Supplied Counties</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/dentistchangemap13_17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/dentistchangemap13_17/</guid>
      <description> NC has moved up in the national rankings of dentists per capita, from 44th in 2013 to 37th in 2017. The majority of the dentist growth in the state occurred in the few counties already well-supplied with dentists, while the supply of dentists relative to population in rural and underserved counties remained largely unchanged.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How has the physician supply changed over time in North Carolina counties?</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/county_physician_beeswarm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/county_physician_beeswarm/</guid>
      <description>Data derived from North Carolina Office of State Budget and Management (OSBM) estimates and projections and physician licensure data from the North Carolina Health Professions Data System (from licensure data provided by the North Carolina Medical Board). Metro and nonmetro delineations are from the United States Office of Management and Budget and applied to Census data.
// Load the Observable runtime and inspector. import {Runtime, Inspector} from &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC Health Professionals are Less Racially and Ethnically Diverse than the General Population.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/workforcediversity2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 18:01:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/workforcediversity2014/</guid>
      <description> The underrepresentation of health professionals who identify as American Indian, Black, and Hispanic in North Carolina’s workforce suggests a lack of equity in opportunity to enter these fields.   More data on NC&amp;rsquo;s health workforce diversity are available here.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Most NC Health Care Jobs are in Allied Health, Nursing, or are Aides/Attendants</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/2016nchealthcarejobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 15:36:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/2016nchealthcarejobs/</guid>
      <description> Two out of every three health care jobs in North Carolina are in allied health or nursing.   Allied health is a broad category that includes many types of professions, such as physical therapists, respiratory therapists, pharmacy technicians, speech-language pathologists, dental hygenists, radiologic technologists, etc.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural residents who are 65 or older are increasing in both number and proportion.</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/rural_young_old_population/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/rural_young_old_population/</guid>
      <description> The increasing population of residents who are 65 or older in rural counties will drive ongoing demand for healthcare services in rural areas. The types of services that health professionals provide in rural areas will also continue to shift, reflecting the needs of an aging population.   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC Health Care Jobs Surpass Manufacturing Jobs in 2009 </title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/manufacturingjobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 15:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/manufacturingjobs/</guid>
      <description> Health care and social services employment in NC has increased since 2000, and maintained steady growth even after the economic recession in 2008.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://example.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/about/</guid>
      <description>The North Carolina Health Professions Data System (HPDS) collects and disseminates descriptive data on selected licensed health professionals in North Carolina. With annual files dating back to 1979, the HPDS is the oldest continuous state health workforce data system in the country.
The HPDS is maintained by the Program on Health Workforce Research and Policy at the Cecil G. Sheps Center for Health Services Research at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, in collaboration with the North Carolina Area Health Education Centers Program (AHEC), and the state’s independent health professional licensing boards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History of the Health Professions Data System</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hpds-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hpds-history/</guid>
      <description>Compiled by Priscilla A. Guild and Gordon H. DeFriese Excerpted from Smith L, Fraher E, Pirani M, et al. A Twenty-Year Profile of Trends in Licensed Health Professions in North Carolina: 1979-1998. October 2000.
In 1973, the Division of Education and Research in Community Medical Care of the UNC Chapel Hill School of Medicine approached the Cecil G. Sheps Center for Health Services Research of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a request that the Center begin efforts to compile a statewide database on physician personnel practicing in North Carolina.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NC Health Professional Licensing Boards</title>
      <link>http://example.org/licensing-boards/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/licensing-boards/</guid>
      <description>NC Board of Chiropractic Examiners
174 Church Street North, Suite 250-R
Concord, NC 28025
Mr. Thomas Sullivan, Executive Director
Email: &amp;#110;&amp;#99;&amp;#x62;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#99;&amp;#101;&amp;#x40;&amp;#x6e;&amp;#99;&amp;#99;&amp;#x68;&amp;#x69;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#x62;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#97;&amp;#114;&amp;#x64;&amp;#x2e;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#x6d;
Phone: (704) 793-1342
Fax: (704) 793-1385
Web: www.ncchiroboard.com
NC Midwifery Joint Committee
PO Box 2129
Raleigh, NC 27602
Ms. Julie George, Executive Director
For data requests: Ms. Julie George, Executive Director, Email: julie@ncbon.com
Phone: (919) 782-3211
Fax (919) 781-9461
Web: www.ncbon.org
NC State Board of Dental Examiners
2000 Perimeter Park Drive, Suite 160</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>